"Benefits and Side Effects of the Shingles Vaccine"
Adult vaccination
can be thought of
as a cornerstone
of successful aging,
but a major issue
hampering the uptake
of shingles vaccination
is the lack of awareness
of the disease.
Shingles is caused
by a reactivation
of the chicken pox virus
later in life.
After your body
beats back chicken pox,
the virus hides in waiting
in your spinal cord,
waiting for an opportunity
to strike back.
When it does,
the virus can surge forth,
traveling along the path
of a nerve
branching off the spinal cord,
wrapping around one side
of the body to the front,
producing skin blisters
along the way
in a characteristic
belt-like pattern
that does not cross
the midline in front.
Both shingles and the name
of the virus, zoster,
are from the Latin and Greek,
respectively, for "belt".
The blistering rash
can be intensely painful
and leave scarring
or discoloration behind,
but usually disappears
in a few weeks on its own.
However, approximately 30
to 50 percent of people suffer
"postherpetic neuralgia,"
persistent pain that can last
for a year or more,
that sometimes
can be debilitating.
Usually, it affects nerves
around your trunk,
but in 10 to 25 percent
of cases,
it can erupt across your face,
which can lead to permanent
facial muscle weakness,
hearing loss,
or blindness.
As if that's all
not bad enough,
having shingles as much
as quintuples your odds
of having a stroke
over the subsequent few weeks,
a risk that gradually declines
over the following
six to twelve months.
It's surprising more people
don't know about it,
since the lifetime risk
of shingles is 30 percent.
Meaning nearly one in three
will get it
sometime in their lives.
Young adults only have
about a 1 in 1,000 chance
of getting it every year,
whereas in older adults
that climbs to closer
to 1 in 100 each year.
That comes out
to a million cases of shingles
every year
in the United States.
Thankfully,
there is a shingles vaccine.
The first became available
in 2006,
using a live weakened strain
of the virus.
The efficacy
was only about 50 percent
and couldn't be used in
immunocompromised individuals,
such as those with HIV
or on immunosuppressive drugs,
such as many on chemotherapy.
Thankfully, in 2017,
a recombinant
shingles vaccine was approved
with a 90 to 97 percent efficacy
for preventing an outbreak.
It requires
two separate injections
2 to 6 months apart,
and is expensive,
like 280 bucks,
but covered by Medicare
and most private
insurance plans.
It also can cause
transient systemic symptoms,
such as muscle aches,
fatigue, headaches,
or fever and chills
serious enough to interfere
with everyday activities
about 10 percent of the time,
but the new vaccine
is considered
so much more effective
that it's recommended
for everyone
starting at age 50,
even if you were previously
immunized with the old one.
Given that the new vaccine
is only about five years old,
longer-term safety
and efficacy data
is still coming in,
but, so far so good.
As soon as I turned 50,
I lined up for mine.